- Over the last 10 years
our web pages have become
more dynamic and powerful
thanks to JavaScript.
We've moved a lot of
code that was normally on
the server side into our browsers,
leaving us with thousands
of lines of JavaScript code
connecting to various HTML and CSS files
with no formal organization.
This is why more and
more developers are using
JavaScript frameworks like,
Angular, React, or Vue.
Vue is an approachable,
versatile, and performant
JavaScript framework
that helps you create
a more maintainable,
and testable code base.
Vue is a progressive JavaScript
framework, which means,
if you have an existing
server-side application,
you can plug Vue into just
one part of your application
that needs a richer, more
interactive experience.
Or, if you want to build
more business logic
into your frontend from the get go,
Vue has the core libraries
and the ecosystem
you'll need to scale.
Like other frontend frameworks,
Vue allows you to take a
web page and split it up
into reusable components,
each having its own HTML,
CSS, and JavaScript needed to render
that piece of the page.
Next, we'll take a look
at Vue in action by
building a product inventory page,
but stay tuned to the end of the video
for a message from
Vue's creator, Evan You.
We won't be teaching you how to use Vue,
but we'll introduce a couple key concepts
that make Vue so useful.
As with many JavaScript applications,
we start from the need to
display data on to our web page.
With Vue, it starts out really simple.
We include the Vue library,
create a Vue instance,
and plug into our root
element with the ID of app.
E L stands for element.
We'll also move our data inside an object
and change X into an expression
with the double curly braces.
As you can see, it works.
Pretty cool, but the magic of
Vue starts when data changes.
If we jump into the console,
we change the value of our product.
Notice that as soon as the
value of product changed,
Vue automatically updated our HTML.
This is because Vue is reactive,
meaning that when our data changes,
Vue takes care of updating all the places
we're using it in our web page.
This works with any kind
of data, not just strings.
So instead of a single product,
let's use an array of products.
Then we'll update our
H2 to an unordered list,
and create a new list item
for each product in the array
using Vue's v-for directive.
This way, each product
gets its own list item
as you see here.
This is still a little contrived though.
So let's start with our list empty
and fetch our products from an actual API
which could be coming
from a database somewhere.
When our app is created,
we'll fetch the latest
products from this API.
All you need to take from it is that
we're fetching our list of products
and updating them in our data.
As you can see on our web page,
each list item is showing
the object it returned.
Well, it's not human readable yet,
so let's change the way it's displayed.
We'll print out quantity and name.
And there it is, printing out nicely.
We might want to call attention to the
items that have quantity zero.
So let's add a little span
with the text, out of stock.
This should only appear if
our item quantity equals zero.
We're going to use the v-if directive.
Because our jacket has quantity
of zero, it's out of stock.
What if we wanted to
print out the total number
of products under our list?
To make this work, we need to create
a computed property called totalProducts
which returns the total
quantity of our products.
If you're not familiar
with JavaScript reduce,
it's adding up all the
quantities from each product.
As you can see, over in our browser,
it's properly adding
up all the quantities.
Here in the browser, I
want to show you Vue's
Chrome plugin where we
can see our array of data
and inspect it right here.
Since we're in the console, just for fun,
let's pop the last item out of the array
and see what happens.
As you can see, not only
is our list updated,
but our total as well, as you would hope.
Next, let's add some
interactivity to this page
through the use of a button.
We'll create an add
button for each product
and when a click occurs,
we'll increment the quantity by one.
Back in the browser, notice
how when we add an item,
not only does the total
inventory get updated,
but also if we increment
our jacket product,
our out of stock notice goes away.
Clicking this button a million times
is going to get tiring,
so what if we wanted to
write in the quantity of
jackets or hiking socks?
We just create a new input
field and bind it to our
product quantity field
with the v-model directive
specifying that it is always a number.
You'll notice now, I can input the total
quantity of each item and
it gets updated immediately.
I can even set the quantity back to zero
and I get my out of stock statement.
And my add buttons still work just fine.
If we were building a larger application,
we might want to split
things up at this point
into their own components and files.
Vue even has a command line interface
which makes it simple to
start real projects quickly.
We might even use single
file Vue components
which contain their own HTML, JavaScript,
and Scoped CSS, or SCSS.
- Hi, I'm Evan You, the creator of Vue.js.
What you've seen here
barely scratched the surface
of what Vue can do.
There's so much more in the ecosystem
to help you build, organize,
and scale your frontend applications.
To get a better taste, read
our documentation today.
I think you'll enjoy the View.